<tool id="FastTree" name="FASTTREE">

    <description>phylogenetic tree builder</description>

    <command>
        FastTreeMP  -quiet -quote $al_type $input_alignment &gt; $output
    </command>

    <inputs>
	<param name="input_alignment"   type="data" format="fasta" label="Select Fasta alignment file" />
	<param name="al_type" type="select" label="Please select type of aligment">
            <option value="-nt">Nucleotide</option>
            <option value="">Protein</option>
        </param>   
    </inputs>

   <outputs>
       <data format="text" name="output" />
   </outputs>
  <help>

**FASTTREE Overview**

FASTTREE_ infers approximately-maximum-likelihood phylogenetic trees from alignments of nucleotide or protein sequences. FastTree can handle alignments with up to a million of sequences in a reasonable amount of time and memory. For large alignments, FastTree is 100-1,000 times faster than PhyML 3.0 or RAxML 7.

.. _FASTTREE: http://www.microbesonline.org/fasttree/

------

**Inputs**

 - Alignmnt file [FASTA, PHYLIP]
 - Alignment Type [Setting]

Note below from the FastTree documentation_ page:

1. If the sequences' names are not unique, then FastTree returns an error.

2. Please make sure that the none of the characters ":,()" appear in your sequence names or you will not be able to parse the resulting tree.

3. Fasta format:

3.1 By default, any text after the first space on a description line will be treated as a comment and will be ignored. For example, the line ">Ecoli arcA protein" is treated as introducing a sequence named "Ecoli". Use the -quote option to change this behavior, or replace spaces with underscores.

3.2 Each description line must be under 5,000 characters long, but sequence lines can be any length.

4. Phylip interleaved format:

4.1 FastTree allows names of any length in phylip files and requires space(s) between the sequence's name and the sequence.

4.2 If you repeat the names of the sequences in succeeding blocks, then the names must match the first block.

4.3 If you do not repeat the names of the sequences in succeeding blocks, then those lines must begin with space(s).

4.4 Each line must be less than 5,000 characters. Longer alignments must be broken up into blocks. (Or use FASTA format: FastTree allows arbitrarily long sequence lines in FASTA format).

4.5 FastTree can read multiple alignments in a single file in phylip format, such as resampled alignments from SEQBOOT, but you need to tell it how many alignments to expect with the -n option.

.. _documentation: http://www.microbesonline.org/fasttree/

------

**Outputs**

 - Tree output file [NEWICK_ format]

.. _NEWICK: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newick_format

------

  </help>
</tool>

